Guide to the Zbigniew Herbert Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Zbigniew Herbert papers
1968-1989
GEN MSS 527
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.84
(3 boxes)
The collection consists chiefly of correspondence and writings relating to Zbigniew Herbert from 1968-1989. There is personal and professional correspondence with Polish literary and cultural figures, publishers, translators and scholars. Noteworthy correspondents include Stanislaw Baranczak, Jozef Czapski, Gustaw Herling-Grudzinski, Konstanty Jelenski, Alina Kalczynska, Susan Sontag, Jacek Trznadel, Petar Vujicic and Adam Zagajewski. Writings include holograph and typescript drafts of essays and poems in the collections Martwa natura z wedzidlem and Elegia na odejscie respectively.
Herbert, Zbigniew, 1924-1998
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Zbigniew Herbert Papers were acquired by purchase in 1989 on the Library Associates Fund.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 3: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Zbigniew Herbert (1924-1998)
Zbigniew Herbert (1924-1998) was a Polish poet and writer whose work has been extensively translated. He was born in Lwow, Poland, and after the war earned degrees in economics, philosophy, and law. His first book of poetry, Struna Swiatla ( Chord of Light ), was published in 1956. Other collections include Hermes, Pies i Gwiazda ( Hermes, a Dog and a Star ), Studium Przedmiotu ( A Study of the Object ), Pan Cogito ( Mr. Cogito ), Raport z Oblezonego Miasta ( Report from the Besieged City ), Elegia na Odejscie ( Elegy for the Departed ), and Martwa Natura z Wedzidlem ( Still Life with a Bridle ). Zbigniew Herbert was survived by his wife Katarzyna Herbert.
Biographical information taken from the online Gale Biography Resource Center.
Scope and Contents
The Zbigniew Herbert Papers consist of letters, manuscripts, and personal papers documenting the life and work of Zbigniew Herbert. The collection spans the years 1968-1989, with the bulk of the material dating from 1985-1989.
The collection is housed in 3 boxes and organized into three series: Correspondence, Writings, and Other Papers. Box 3 contains Restricted Fragile Papers.
Series I, Correspondence, consists of incoming letters from over 30 correspondents, as well as a number of outgoing items, including a series of postcards from the poet to his wife. The majority of the correspondence is in Polish, but there is material in German, English, French, and Italian in the collection. All but one of the letters were written between the years 1985 and 1989.
The correspondence allows a glimpse of the poet's private and professional life, as it comprises messages from publishers, translators, fellow writers, and friends. These include the Polish painter and writer Jozef Czapski, as well as the poet's translator into Serbo-Croatian, Petar Vujicic.
The Czapski file includes an outgoing message, several handwritten notes, and seven typed letters in which the 90-year-old painter shares his opinions and feelings on issues of poetry, art, politics, Polish history, and morality.
The Petar Vujicic file contains only two letters, but they appear to provide the context to a poem Herbert dedicated to his Yugoslavian translator. Vujicic writes about the importance of Herbert's poetry in his country, explains his choices for a Herbert anthology, and draws a parallel between the political situations in Poland and Yugoslavia.
Other noteworthy correspondents represented in the collection include Konstanty Jelenski, the literary critic and historian Jacek Trznadel, the poets Adam Zagajewski and Stanislaw Baranczak, and writers at the American Center of P.E.N.
Series II, Writings, includes notes, holograph and typescript drafts, and copies of final versions of four poems from the collection Elegia na Odejscie (1990) and five essays from the collection Martwa Natura z Wedzidlem (1993). The series is subdivided into autobiographical writings, essays, and poems, with individual essays and poems arranged alphabetically by title. The materials illustrate Herbert's writing and editing methods. Manuscripts are often represented by notes and multiple drafts, and manuscript leaves often appear on the versos of correspondence and documentation. Where multiple drafts are present, they are arranged chronologically. Where leaves appear on the versos of correspondence from individuals or institutions with established name headings, cross-references have been added to the finding aid from the correspondence to the writings.
Series III, Other Papers, includes addresses and a list of names.
Restricted Fragile Papers are housed in box 3.
Authors, Polish -- 20th Century -- Archives; European literature -- 20th Century; Polish literature -- 20th Century; Poland; Authors; Barańczak, Stanisław, 1946-2014; Czapski, Józef, 1896-1993; Herbert, Zbigniew, 1924-1998; Herling-Grudziński, Gustaw, 1919-2000; Jeleński, Konstanty A. (Konstanty Aleksander), 1922-1987; Kalczyńska, Alina, 1936-; Sontag, Susan, 1933-2004; Trznadel, Jacek; Vujic̆ić, Petar; Zagajewski, Adam, 1945-
- Correspondence, 1968-1989; Series I; 0.21; (.5 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is organized into two subseries: General Correspondence and Third Party Correspondence.
  - GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE
    - "A" General, 1968 Dec 20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Akademie der Künste (Berlin, Germany)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Writings, Essays, Martwa Natura z Wedzidlem, "Delta," Box 1, folder 44; Poetry, Elegia na Odejscie, "Prosba," Box 2, folder 59; and "Smierc Lwa," Box 2, folder 63
    - Akzente, 1986 Dec 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - American Center of P.E.N., 1987-88 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Includes letters from Herbert to American Center of P.E.N. and letter from Susan Sontag
    - Aridjis, Homero, 1987 Mar 16 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "B" General, 1986 Nov 28 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Baranczak, Stanislaw, 1988 Dec 26 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes color photograph of Baranczak's family
    - Bayerische Akademie der Schonen Künste, 1986-87, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      See also: Writings, Essays, Martwa Natura z Wedzidlem, "Delta," Box 1, folder 44
    - Bielecki, Czeslaw, 1987 Apr 6 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bienkowski, Zbigniew, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Brodsky, Joseph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Includes note from Adam Zagajewski to Herbert
    - Bronski, Maciej, 1988 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Carl Hanser Verlag, 1986 Dec 22 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Chrzanowski, Tadeusz, 1987 Jan 19 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Czapski, Jozef, 1986-89, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Includes letter from Herbert to Czapski and enclosures
    - Deutsche Akademie für Sprache und Dichtung, 1987 Jan 29 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Dzieduszycka, Teresa, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Note [in Czapski's hand?]
    - "G" General, 1987 Feb 2 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Glasson Deschaumes, Ghislaine
      See: Writings, Poetry, "Prosba," Box 2, folder 59
    - Hamburger, Michael, 1986 Nov 29 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Herbert, Katarzyna, 1986-87, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Letters from Zbigniew to Katarzyna Herbert
    - Herling-Grudzinski, Gustaw, 1987-88, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Instytut Literacki (Paris, France), 1989 Feb 27 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Jelenski, Konstanty A. (Konstanty Aleksander), 1985-87 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Includes letter from Herbert to Jelenski
    - Kalczynska, Alina; Scheiwiller, Vanni, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Includes copies of third-party letters
    - Landais, Hubert (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Letter from Herbert to Landais
    - Marchesani, Pietro, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Musy, [Jean?], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Letter from Herbert to Musy
    - New York Review of Books, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Nowakowski, Marek, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Scheiwiller, Vanni
      See: Kalczynska, Alina, Box 1, folder 23
    - Sklarew, Myra, 1986-87 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Sontag, Susan
      See: American Center of P.E.N., Box 1, folder 3
    - Suhrkamp Verlag
      See: Writings, Essays, Martwa Natura z Wedzidlem, "Cena Sztuki," Box 1, folder 41
    - Sulik, Boleslaw, 1986 Aug 4 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Szczepanski, Jan Jozef, 1987 Jan 6 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Trznadel, Jacek, 1987 Jan 17 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Vujicic, Petar, 1987 Jan (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Wozniakowski, Jacek, 1987 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Zagajewski, Adam, 1987 Jan 25 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      Includes card signed by Stella Johnston and others
      See also: Brodsky, Joseph, Box 1, folder 10
    - Unidentified, 1989 Jan 5 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - THIRD PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Letters to Konstanty Jelenski
      - Douchy, Therese, 1985 Aug 6 (Box 1, Folder 37)
        Includes memo from Herbert
      - Gallimard (Firm), 1985-86 (Box 1, Folder 38)
        Includes letters from Jelenski to firm and drafts of translations into French of Herbert poems
      - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Writings, 1987-1988; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series II, Writings, is organized into three subseries, Autobiographical Writings, Essays, and Poetry, and arranged alphabetically by title within each subseries.
  - AUTOBIOGRAPHICAL WRITINGS
    - ["Jestem przede wszystkim pisarzem..."], holograph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - ESSAYS
    - Martwa Natura z Wedzidlem
      "Cena sztuki"
      - Notes and drafts, holograph (Box 1, Folder 41)
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - Draft, typescript, corrected (photocopy), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 43)
      - "Delta"
        - Notes and drafts, holograph and typescript (Box 1, Folder 44)
          Includes correspondence and documentation on versos of manuscript leaves, including completed form for Fondation pour une entraide intellectuelle européene
        - Draft, typescript and typescript carbon (incomplete), corrected (Box 1, Folder 45)
        - Draft, typescript, corrected (photocopy), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 46)
      - "Gerard Terboch: Dyskretny urok mieszczanstwa"
        - Notes and drafts, holograph, corrected (Box 1, Folder 47)
        - Draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 48)
        - Draft, typescript and typescript carbon, corrected (Box 1, Folder 49)
        - Draft, typescript, corrected (photocopy), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 50)
      - "Temat nie bohaterski"
        - Draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 51)
        - Draft, typescript, corrected (photocopy), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 52)
      - "Tulipanow gorzki zapach"
        - Draft, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 53)
        - Draft, typescript, corrected (photocopy), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - POETRY
    - Elegia na Odejscie
      "Domysly na temat Barabasza"
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 55)
      - Draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 56)
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 57)
      - Final draft, typescript (photocopy), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 58)
      - "Prosba"
        - Drafts, holograph, corrected, [ca. 1987] (Box 2, Folder 59)
          Includes letters on versos of leaves
        - Draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 60)
        - Draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 61)
        - Final draft, typescript (photocopy), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 62)
      - "Smierc Lwa"
        - Drafts, holograph, corrected, [ca. 1988] (Box 2, Folder 63)
        - Draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 64)
        - Draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 65)
        - Final draft, typescript, corrected (photocopy), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 66)
      - "Woz"
        - Draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 67)
        - Draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 68)
        - Draft, holograph, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 69)
        - Final draft, typescript, corrected (photocopy), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 70)
- Other Papers, Series III; 2
  Series III, Other Papers, is arranged by type of material.
  - Addresses, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - List of names, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 72)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.21; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 14 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Box 1, folder 42 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Box 1, folder 44 (Box 3, Folder 75)